Digital Tale of Genji - Feature Introduction.
デジタル源氏物語、機能紹介。
We will explain "Viewing Images and Text Together."
「画像とテキストを一緒にみる」についてご説明します。
Access "View Images and Text Together" from the menu.
メニュー画面から「画像とテキストを一緒にみる」にアクセスします。
Click the menu item on the left side.
左側のメニューをクリックしてください。
This is the top page.
こちらがトップ画面です。
You can browse the following images.
以下の画像を一覧できます。
The Tale of Genji (Todai manuscript) and Old Movable Type Edition (Kyudai manuscript).
源氏物語（東大本）、古活字版（九大本）。
Muketsu Mukankisheihanbon, Kogetsusho, and Koigenji Monogatari.
無欠無刊記整版本、湖月抄、校異源氏物語です。
Click "View Images and Text Together" to open the viewer.
「画像とテキストを一緒にみる」ボタンをクリックして開きます。
You can access each resource with one click via "Related Links."
「関連リンク」から各データにワンクリックでアクセスできます。
Links to Koigenji Monogatari, modern translations, and Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu.
校異源氏物語、現代語訳、新編日本古典文学全集へのリンクがあります。
This is the screen for viewing original images and text together.
原本画像と本文テキストを一緒にみる画面です。
A Parallel Text Viewer utilizing TEI and IIIF.
TEIとIIIFを活用したParallel Text Viewerです。
Original images on the left, main text on the upper right, modern translation on the lower right.
左側に原本画像、右上に本文、右下に現代語訳が表示されます。
Unwanted images can be hidden with the "x" button.
不要な画像は「×」ボタンで非表示にできます。
Closing images one by one.
画像を閉じていきます。
You can display only the original images you need in a larger view.
必要な原本画像だけを大きく表示できます。
You can compare the Todai and Kyudai old movable type manuscripts side by side.
東大本と九大本の古活字版を並べて比較できます。
This allows comparison between different manuscripts.
写本同士を比較することができます。
We will introduce how to read related materials via original images.
原本画像経由で関連資料を読む方法をご紹介します。
Please note the ginkgo leaf marks on the images.
画像上の銀杏マークに注目してください。
Orange ginkgo marks link to the Koigenji Monogatari.
オレンジ色の銀杏マークは校異源氏物語へのリンクです。
Blue ginkgo marks link to the Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu.
青色の銀杏マークは新編日本古典文学全集へのリンクです。
Hover over them to see the link destination.
マウスオンでリンク先が表示されます。
Click the orange ginkgo mark to access the Koigenji Monogatari.
オレンジ色の銀杏マークから校異源氏物語へアクセスします。
You can zoom in on the Todai manuscript image for detailed viewing.
東大本の原本画像をズームして閲覧できます。
Clicking opens the National Diet Library Digital Collection.
銀杏マークをクリックすると、国立国会図書館デジタルコレクションが開きます。
The page is loading.
該当ページの読み込み中です。
The corresponding page of the Koigenji Monogatari is now displayed.
校異源氏物語の該当ページが表示されました。
You can view it on the National Diet Library Digital Collection.
国立国会図書館デジタルコレクションで閲覧できます。
Next, click the blue ginkgo mark.
続いて、青色の銀杏マークをクリックします。
This links to the Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu.
新編日本古典文学全集へのリンクです。
JapanKnowledge offers both a Lib edition and a Personal edition.
ジャパンナレッジにはLib版とPersonal版があります。
Clicking the blue ginkgo mark opens JapanKnowledge.
青色の銀杏マークをクリックすると、ジャパンナレッジが開きます。
You can read the Shinpen Nihon Koten Bungaku Zenshu text on JapanKnowledge Lib.
ジャパンナレッジLibで新編日本古典文学全集の本文を閲覧できます。
For the Personal edition, please log in with your own account.
Personal版はご自身のアカウントでログインしてください。
After logging in, you can view the corresponding sections.
ログイン後、同様に該当箇所を閲覧できます。
Here is how to view the Tale of Genji via the Koigenji Monogatari.
校異源氏物語経由で源氏物語をみる方法です。
IIIF icons are displayed at the top of each page.
IIIFアイコンが各ページ先頭に表示されています。
Clicking the IIIF icon displays the corresponding section of the original images.
IIIFアイコンをクリックすると、原本画像の対応箇所が表示されます。
The original images are displayed automatically.
原本画像が自動的に表示されます。
Multiple original images are shown side by side.
複数の原本画像が並んで表示されます。
You can compare corresponding sections across different manuscripts.
各写本の該当箇所を比較できます。
Orange ginkgo marks indicate the corresponding sections.
オレンジ色の銀杏マークで該当箇所を示しています。
You can compare multiple manuscripts simultaneously.
複数の写本を同時に比較できます。
Let us explain the anchor marks.
碇マークについてご説明します。
They are displayed at the beginning of each line in the Koigenji Monogatari.
校異源氏物語の各行先頭に表示されています。
Clicking highlights the corresponding section in the modern translation.
クリックすると現代語訳の対応箇所がハイライト表示されます。
Hovering over the modern translation highlights the corresponding anchor mark.
現代語訳にマウスオンすると、対応する碇マークがハイライトされます。
Digital Tale of Genji.
デジタル源氏物語。
Thank you for watching.
Digital Tale of Genji。